<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>seminar on DinAmicI</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/tags/seminar/</link><description>Recent content in seminar on DinAmicI</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 20:08:54 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.dinamici.org/tags/seminar/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Seminar Prof. Heinz Hanssmann (University of Utrecht)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/2016/02/seminar-prof-heinz-hanssmann-university-of-utrecht/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 20:08:54 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/2016/02/seminar-prof-heinz-hanssmann-university-of-utrecht/</guid><description>&lt;p>Prof. Heinz Hanssmann (University of Utrecht)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>“Families of hyperbolic Hamiltonian tori”&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thursday 11 February 2016,  15.00&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dipartimento di Matematica (aula Dal Passo) Università di Roma “Tor
Vergata”&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Abstract:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In integrable Hamiltonian systems hyperbolic tori form families,
parametrised by the actions conjugate to the toral angles. The union
over such a family is a normally hyperbolic invariant manifold. Under
Diophantine conditions a hyperbolic torus persists a small perturbation
away from integrability. Locally around such a torus the normally
hyperbolic invariant manifold is the centre manifold of that torus and
persists as well. We are interested in `global’ persistence of the
normally hyperbolic invariant manifold. An important aspect is how the
dynamics behaves at the (topological) boundary. Where the manifold
extends to infinity this boundary is empty – this case makes clear that
we need the persistence theorem of normally hyperbolic invariant
manifolds in the non-compact setting. If the normal hyperbolicity wanes
as the boundary is approached we need to ensure that the perturbed
dynamics does not come closer to the boundary. This provides the
necessary uniform lower bound of normal hyperbolicity to still ascertain
persistence under small perturbations. Making use of energy preservation
and of Diophantine tori persisting by KAM theory this can be achieved
for families of two-dimensional hyperbolic tori.&lt;/p>
&lt;p> &lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bruin's seminar in Pisa</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/10/bruins-seminar-in-pisa/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2015 13:06:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/10/bruins-seminar-in-pisa/</guid><description>&lt;p>Thursday 12th November 2015, h 9:30 Sala Conferenze, Collegio Puteano,
Centro De Giorgi, Pisa&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Henk Bruin (University of Vienna)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Sharp mixing rates via inducing with respect to general return times&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Abstract: For non-uniformly expanding maps inducing w.r.t. a general
(i.e., not necessarily first) return time to Gibbs Markov maps, we
provide sufficient conditions for obtaining sharp estimates for the
correlation function. This applies to both the finite and the infinite
measure setting. The results are illustrated by non-Markov intervals
maps with an indifferent fixed point. This is joint work with Dalia
Terhesiu.&lt;/p>
&lt;p> &lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Pollicott's seminar in Pisa</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/09/pollicotts-seminar-in-pisa/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 17:21:05 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/09/pollicotts-seminar-in-pisa/</guid><description>&lt;p>Thursday  03/9/2015, h 16:30 Sala Conferenze (Puteano, Centro De Giorgi)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mark Pollicott (University of Warwick)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>“LINEAR RESPONSE AND PERIODIC ORBITS”&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Cellarosi's seminar in Bologna, July 22, 2015</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/07/cellarosis-seminar-in-bologna-july-22-2015/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 08:58:17 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/07/cellarosis-seminar-in-bologna-july-22-2015/</guid><description>&lt;p>When: Wednesday July 22, 2015, at 11:30&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Where: Seminario I, Dept. of Mathematics, Università di Bologna&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Who: Francesco Cellarosi (Queen&amp;rsquo;s University, Canada)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What: Seminar &amp;ldquo;Recent progress towards Sarnak’s and Chowla’s
Conjectures&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Abstract: I will present an overview of Sarnak’s conjecture on the
disjointness of the Möbius function from any deterministic sequence and
the related Chowla’s conjecture on the self-correlations of the Möbius
function. Some progress towards weaker versions of these conjectures
have been made recently, and I plan to
illustrate them.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>De Simoi's seminar in Pisa</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/07/de-simois-seminar-in-pisa/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 08:46:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/07/de-simois-seminar-in-pisa/</guid><description>&lt;p>Monday  20/7/2015, h 11:30-12:30 Sala Conferenze (Puteano, Centro De
Giorgi)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Jacopo De Simoi (University of Toronto)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;AN INTEGRABLE BILLIARD CLOSE TO AN ELLIPSE OF SMALL ECCENTRICITY IS AN
ELLIPSE&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Abstract: In 1927 G. Birkhoff conjectured that if a billiard in a
strictly convex smooth domain is integrable, the domain has to be an
ellipse (or a circle). The conjecture is still wide open, and presents
remarkable relations with open questions in inverse spectral theory and
spectral rigidity. In the talk we show that a version of Birkhoff&amp;rsquo;s
conjecture is true for small perturbations of ellipses of small
eccentricity. This is joint work with A. Avila and V. Kaloshin&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Vaienti's seminar in Pisa</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/07/seminario-di-vaienti-a-pisa/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2015 15:24:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/07/seminario-di-vaienti-a-pisa/</guid><description>&lt;p>Friday, July 17, 2015, h. 16:00-17:00 Sala Conferenze (Puteano, Centro
De Giorgi)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sandro Vaienti (CPT Marseille)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;On recent results of extreme value theory applied to dynamical systems&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Abstract:  We give a review of a few recent results of extreme value
theory applied to random dynamical systems and to coupled lattice maps.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>