<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Dai-Seminar on DinAmicI</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/categories/dai-seminar/</link><description>Recent content in Dai-Seminar on DinAmicI</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 08:39:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.dinamici.org/categories/dai-seminar/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Jacopo De Simoi (University of Toronto) and Carlangelo Liverani (Università di Roma Tor Vergata)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/2024-12-desimoi-liverani/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 08:39:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/2024-12-desimoi-liverani/</guid><description>&lt;p>Speaker: Jacopo De Simoi (University of Toronto)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Title: Statistical properties of some mostly expanding fast-slow partially hyperbolic systems&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Abstract: In this joint work with K. Fernando and N. Fleming-Vázquez, we consider a class of sufficiently smooth two-dimensional fast-slow
partially hyperbolic systems. This class is obtained by perturbing a trivial extension of a one-parameter family of one-dimensional expanding maps.
We assume that the averaged system has exactly one sink and that both Lyapunov exponents of the system are positive.
Using an elaboration on the technique of standard pairs, we will show that, for su ciently small perturbations, there
exists a unique SRB measure for the system; we also show that the system exhibits exponential decay of correlations for Hölder
observables with explicit, nearly optimal bounds. This work is a &amp;ldquo;mostly expanding&amp;rdquo; counterpart of the analogous result
for &amp;ldquo;mostly contracting&amp;rdquo; systems (i.e. with one negative Lyapunov exponent) which was studied in a joint work with C. Liverani several years ago.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Speaker: Carlangelo Liverani (Università di Roma Tor Vergata)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Title: Some open problems and considerations at the intersection of partially hyperbolic systems, randomness, and statistical mechanics&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Abstract:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>NOTE: The seminars will be streamed live on our YouTube channel then saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Adam Kanigowski (University of Maryland) and Kosma Kasprzak (Jagiellonian University, Krakow)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/2024-10-kanigowski-kasprzak/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 14:39:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/2024-10-kanigowski-kasprzak/</guid><description>&lt;p>Speaker: Adam Kanigowski (University of Maryland),&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Title: Ergodic Theorems along sparse subsets of the integers&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Abstract: Let $A$ be a subset of the positive integers. For a dynamical system $(X,T)$ we are interested in ergodic averages along $A$, i.e. for $x\in X$ and $f\in C(X)$ we look at the limiting behavior of $\frac{1}{|A_N|}\sum_{k\in A_N}f(T^kx)$, where $A_N=\{ k\in A: k\leq N \}$.
We will focus on the case where $A$ is the set of primes or values of polynomials with integer coefficients. We will recall some classical results, mention some recent developments and highlight some interesting open problems.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Speaker: Kosma Kasprzak (Jagiellonian University, Krakow)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Title: Ergodicity along square orbits in rigid dynamical systems&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Abstract: In this talk we will focus on topological dynamical systems exhibiting rigidity; that is, systems $(X, T)$ where some sequence of iterates $T^{q_n}$ approaches the identity function on $X$. It turns out, that a variant of this property gives us control over the ergodic averages along squares for any starting point $x\in X$. We will showcase this original result, discuss its proof and provide a class of examples of systems satisfying the assumptions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>NOTE: The seminars will be streamed live on our YouTube channel then saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Tanja I. Schindler (Jagiellonian University, Krakow) and Jon Aaronson (Tel Aviv University)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/2024-06-schindler-aaronson/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2024 17:39:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/2024-06-schindler-aaronson/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Tanja I. Schindler&lt;/strong> (Jagiellonian University, Krakow),&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Properties and limit laws of dynamical systems with two infinite components&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> While studying dynamical systems with one infinite component, i.e. a probability preserving dynamical system and a non-integrable observable or an infinite measure preserving dynamical system with an integrable observable still has a lot of interesting questions - it is interesting to study systems with more than one infinite component. An example would be an infinite measure system with an observable which is not integrable on a finite measure set. Another example would be a dynamical system with two dynamically separated infinite measure sets A and B; i.e. orbits have to pass through a finite measure set Y in order to pass from A to B and vice versa. I will show some (completely incomplete list of) examples where one of the above described behaviours occur. This is a somewhat expository talk including joint work with Claudio Bonanno and Muhammad Mubarak.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Jon Aaronson&lt;/strong> (Tel Aviv University)
&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Open problems in Infinite Ergodic Theory&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> tba.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminars will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Tere M-Seara (Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya) and Jaime Paradela Diaz (University of Maryland)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/2024-05-seara-paradela/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 12:39:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/2024-05-seara-paradela/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Tere M-Seara&lt;/strong> (Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya),&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Unstable motions in the Three Body Problem&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> Since the works of Johannes Kepler (1571-1630), and later the works of Isaac Newton (1642-1727) about the universal laws of
gravitation, it is well known that the possible motion of two bodies moving under their mutual Newtonian gravitational forces can be on
ellipses, parabolas or hyperbolas.
In this talk we will recall Kepler results about the motion of two bodies and we will talk about the possible motions when one considers
the more realistic model of three bodies.
This problem, already considered by Henri Poincaré (1854-1912), is still far for being understood, and one can found many works proving
the existence of different type of solutions for the three body problem like periodic orbits, asymptotic orbits to them, among others.
In this talk we will give some light about the possible motions that three bodies can have if we wait enough time and we will try to
answer questions like:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Will the orbits be bounded or can the bodies fall apart (and therefore going to &amp;ldquo;infinity&amp;rdquo;)?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Can one find chaotic motion in the three body problem and therefore unpredictability?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>These and related questions will be the main goals of this talk, where we will see how the mathematical tools coming from Dynamical Systems
can be used to deal with this complex problem.
In particular, we will prove the existence of of oscillatory motions, that is, orbits which leave every bounded region but which return
infinitely often to some fixed bounded region.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>Speaker: &lt;strong>Jaime Paradela Diaz&lt;/strong> (University of Maryland)
&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Homoclinic tangencies of parabolic saddles and Newhouse domains in Celestial Mechanics&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> Consider a one-parameter family of smooth surface diffeomorphisms unfolding a quadratic homoclinic tangency to a hyperbolic fixed point. It is well known that in this unfolding there exists a Newhouse domain, i.e. an open set of parameters for which the corresponding diffeomorphisms exhibit persistent homoclinic tangencies. Moreover, quite a number of surprisingly exotic dynamical phenomena have been shown to exist for residual sets of parameters contained in the Newhouse domain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The analysis of the unfolding is certainly more subtle when the homoclinic tangency is associated to a persistent degenerate saddle, i.e. a parabolic fixed point which exists for all values of the parameter and for which the topological picture of the local dynamics resembles that of a hyperbolic fixed point (existence of invariant manifolds and C^0 Lambda lemma). These degenerate saddles appear naturally in several models in Celestial Mechanics, in particular, in the so-called restricted 4 Body Problem. We prove that, in a particular configuration of the latter model which can be reduced to an area preserving map, there exists a degenerate saddle with a quadratic homoclinic tangency that unfolds generically (as we move the masses of the bodies). Moreover, and despite the fact that the C^1 Lambda lemma does not hold for this degenerate saddle, we show that the dynamics at the unfolding of the tangency can be renormalized, with the critical Hénon map showing up in the limit process. This implies the existence of a Newhouse domain in the parameter space (the masses of the bodies) and a residual subset of parameters for which there exist hyperbolic sets of large Hausdorff dimension which are accumulated by elliptic islands. This is joint work with J.M. Garrido and P. Martín.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminars will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Kasun Fernando (University of Toronto, Canada)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/kasun-fernando-university-of-toronto-canada/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 08:33:27 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/kasun-fernando-university-of-toronto-canada/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Mauro Artigiani (Universidad del Rosario, Colombia)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/mauro-artigiani-universidad-del-rosario-colombia/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 08:31:10 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/mauro-artigiani-universidad-del-rosario-colombia/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Matteo Tanzi (New York University, USA)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/matteo-tanzi-new-york-university-usa/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 08:28:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/matteo-tanzi-new-york-university-usa/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Matteo Tanzi&lt;/strong> (New York University, USA)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Random-like properties of chaotic forcing&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> We prove that skew systems with a sufficiently expanding
base have &amp;ldquo;approximate&amp;rdquo; statistical properties similar to random ergodic
Markov chains. For example, they exhibit approximate exponential decay
of correlations, meaning that the exponential rate is observed modulo a
controlled error. The fiber maps are only assumed to be Lipschitz
regular and to depend on the base in a way that guarantees diffusive
behaviour on the vertical component. The assumptions do not imply an
hyperbolic picture and one cannot rely on the spectral properties of the
transfer operators involved. The approximate nature of the result is the
inevitable price one pays for having so mild assumptions on the dynamics
on the vertical component. The error in the approximation is shown to go
to zero when the expansion of the base tends to infinity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Umberto Zannier (Scuola Normale Superiore, Italy)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/umberto-zannier-scuola-normale-superiore-italy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Apr 2021 08:40:46 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/umberto-zannier-scuola-normale-superiore-italy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Umberto Zannier&lt;/strong>  (Scuola Normale Superiore, Italy)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Torsion values of sections, elliptical billiards and
diophantine problems in dynamics&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> After a very brief review of basics on elliptic curves and
their families, we shall consider &amp;ldquo;sections&amp;rdquo; of such  families, and
especially their &amp;ldquo;torsion values&amp;rdquo;.  For instance, what can be said of
the complex numbers b for which [latex](2, \sqrt{2(2-b)})[/latex]
is torsion on the Legendre curve [latex]y^2=x(x-1)(x-b)[/latex]? In
particular, we shall recall results of &amp;ldquo;Manin-Mumford type&amp;rdquo; and focus to
illustrate some applications to elliptical billiards. Finally, if time
allows we shall frame these issues as special cases of a general
question in arithmetic dynamics, which can be treated with different
methods, depending on the context.&lt;br>
(Most results refer to work with Pietro Corvaja and David Masser.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Selim Ghazouani (Université d’Orsay, France)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/selim-ghazouani-universite-dorsay-france/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 21:04:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/selim-ghazouani-universite-dorsay-france/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Selim Ghazouani&lt;/strong> (Université d’Orsay, France)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Piecewise affine homeomorphisms of the circle and dilation
surfaces&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> In this talk I will consider the following question: if one
picks a piecewise affine map of the circle &amp;ldquo;at random”, what dynamical
behaviour are we likely to observe? The case of standard circle
diffeomorphisms has been studied by Herman in the 80s; in this
emblematic case the problem can be reduced to theorems close to KAM
theory. For the piecewise affine case, we put forward a geometric
approach, inspired by methods from both Teichmüller theory and
hyperbolic geometry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Tanja Schindler (Scuola Normale Superiore, Italy)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/tanja-schindler-scuola-normale-superiore-italy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 22:04:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/tanja-schindler-scuola-normale-superiore-italy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Tanja Schindler&lt;/strong>  (Scuola Normale Superiore, Italy)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Almost sure asymptotic behaviour of Birkhoff sums for infinite
measure-preserving dynamical systems&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> We are interested in the limit behaviour of Birkhoff sums
over an infinite sigma-finite measure space. If the observable is
integrable then &amp;ndash; by a classical theorem by Aaronson &amp;ndash; there exists no
sequence of real numbers such that the Birkhoff sum normed by this
sequence converges almost surely to 1. Under strong mixing conditions on
the underlying system we prove a generalized strong law of large numbers
for integrable observables using a truncated sum adding a suitable
number of terms depending on the point of evaluation. For f not
integrable we give conditions on f such that the Birkhoff sum normed by
a sequence of real numbers converges almost surely to 1. Joint work with
Claudio Bonanno.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Eva Miranda (Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya) and Daniel Peralta-Salas (Instituto de Ciencias Matemáticas, Spain)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/eva-miranda-universitat-politecnica-de-catalunya-and-daniel-peralta-salas-instituto-de-ciencias-matematicas-spain/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 09:39:26 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/eva-miranda-universitat-politecnica-de-catalunya-and-daniel-peralta-salas-instituto-de-ciencias-matematicas-spain/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speakers:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Eva Miranda&lt;/strong> (Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya),
&lt;strong>Daniel Peralta-Salas&lt;/strong> (Instituto de Ciencias Matemáticas, Spain)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Looking at Euler flows through a contact mirror: Universality
and Turing completeness&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> The dynamics of an inviscid and incompressible fluid flow on
a Riemannian manifold is governed by the Euler equations. Recently, Tao
launched a programme to address the global existence problem for the
Euler and Navier Stokes equations based on the concept of universality.
Inspired by this proposal, we show that the stationary Euler equations
exhibit several universality features, In the sense that, any
non-autonomous flow on a compact manifold can be extended to a smooth
stationary solution of the Euler equations on some Riemannian manifold
of possibly higher dimension. These results can be viewed as lending
support to the intuition that solutions to the Euler equations can be
extremely complicated in nature. A key point in the proof is looking at
the h-principle in contact geometry through a contact mirror, unveiled
by Sullivan, Etnyre and Ghrist more than two decades ago. We end up this
talk addressing an apparently different question: What kind of physics
might be non-computational? Using the former universality result, we can
establish the Turing completeness of the steady Euler flows, i.e., there
exist solutions that encode a universal Turing machine and, in
particular, these solutions have undecidable trajectories. But, in view
of the increase of dimension yielded by our proof, the question is: can
this be done in dimension 3? We will prove the existence of Turing
complete fluid flows on a 3-dimensional geometric domain. Our novel
strategy uses the computational power of symbolic dynamics and the
contact mirror again.&lt;br>
This talk is based on joint work with Robert Cardona and Fran Presas
(&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1911.01963">arXiv:1911.01963&lt;/a> and
&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.12828">arXiv:2012.12828&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Álvaro del Pino Gómez (Utrecht University, The Netherlands)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/alvaro-del-pino-gomez/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 15:14:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/alvaro-del-pino-gomez/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Álvaro del Pino Gómez&lt;/strong>  (Utrecht University, The
Netherlands)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Billiards in subriemannian geometry&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> When one considers manifolds with boundary, billiard
dynamics are the natural analogue of standard geodesic dynamics. Namely,
instead of having geodesics escape at the boundary, we force them back
into the manifold using the reflection law. In other dynamical settings,
similar constructions are possible: In 2006, B. Khesin and S.
Tabachnikov initiated the study of billiards in the semiriemannian
setting, studying the integrability of various tables. In recent years
we have also seen the appearance of several billiard setups of
symplectic nature. In this talk I will discuss recent work with L.
Dahinden in which we look at billiards in subriemannian geometry. I will
sketch how the reflection law arises naturally both from the
control-theoretical and symplectic perspectives, how the reflection is
problematic at tangency points between the distribution and the boundary
of the table, and I will introduce some concrete examples. My ultimate
goal will be to pose several intriguing open questions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Alessandro Della Corte (Università di Camerino, Italy)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/alessandro-della-corte-universita-di-camerino-italy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 16:22:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/alessandro-della-corte-universita-di-camerino-italy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Alessandro Della Corte&lt;/strong>  (Università di Camerino, Italy)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>The simplest erasing substitution&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> The symbolic action of a substitution on the binary
expansion generates naturally an interval map. In case of erasing
substitutions, the map is typically Baire-1 and not Darboux. As a model
case, we consider what is arguably the simplest erasing substitution,
mapping 0s to the empty word and 1s to 0 or 1 depending on the parity.
The corresponding interval map is shown to have fractal properties
(bounds are given on the Hausdorff dimension of the fibers) and to
display rich dynamical behavior, including Devaney chaos, uniform
distributional chaos of type 1, infinite topological entropy as well as
the presence of cycles attracting in a finite time every rational.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Paolo Giulietti (Università di Pisa, Italy)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/paolo-giulietti-universita-di-pisa-italy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 15:15:05 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/paolo-giulietti-universita-di-pisa-italy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Paolo Giulietti&lt;/strong>  (Università di Pisa, Italy)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Infinite mixing for accessible skew products&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> I will present some decay of correlations results on skew
products which are locally accessible. The results rely on the study of
a twisted transfer operator and could be generalized to many other
situations. I will also present numerical counterparts to such results.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Gary Froyland (University of New South Wales, Australia)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/gary-froyland-university-of-new-south-wales-australia/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 12:12:10 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/gary-froyland-university-of-new-south-wales-australia/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Gary Froyland&lt;/strong> (University of New South Wales, Australia)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>The dynamic ocean&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> The circulation of our oceans strongly influences climate,
weather and biology. Our ocean currents are dynamic, and fluctuate to
varying extents. I will introduce data-driven numerical tools that can
tease apart dynamic components of the ocean, with information sourced
from ocean drifters, satellite imagery, and ocean models. These
components, their lifecycles, and their response to external forcing,
help us to build a dynamic picture of our ocean.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Misha Bialy (Tel Aviv University, Israel)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/mischa-bialy-tel-aviv-university-israel/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 08:29:01 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/mischa-bialy-tel-aviv-university-israel/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> **Misha Bialy ** (Tel Aviv University, Israel)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Birkhoff-Poritsky conjecture for centrally-symmetric billiards&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> In this talk I shall discuss Birkhoff-Poritsky conjecture
for centrally-symmetric C^2-smooth convex planar billiards. We assume
that the domain A between the invariant curve of 4-periodic orbits and
the boundary of the phase cylinder is foliated by C^0-invariant curves.
Under this assumption we prove that the billiard curve is an ellipse.
Other versions of Birkhoff-Poritsky conjecture follow from this result.
For the original Birkhoff-Poritsky formulation we show that if a
neighborhood of the boundary of billiard domain has a C^1-smooth
foliation by convex caustics of rotation numbers in the interval (0;
1/4] then the boundary curve is an ellipse. The main ingredients of the
proof are: (1) the non-standard generating function for convex
billiards; (2) the remarkable structure of the invariant curve
consisting of 4-periodic orbits; and (3) the integral-geometry approach
initiated by the author for rigidity results of circular billiards.
Surprisingly, we establish a Hopf-type rigidity for billiards in the
ellipse. Based on joint work with Andrey E. Mironov (Novosibirsk).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Michele Gianfelice (Università della Calabria, Italy)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/michele-gianfelice-universita-della-calabria-italy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 13:27:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/michele-gianfelice-universita-della-calabria-italy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Michele Gianfelice&lt;/strong>  (Università della Calabria, Italy)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Stochastic stability of classical Lorenz flow under impulsive
type forcing&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> Inspired by the problem of modeling the so called
anthropogenic forcing in climatology, e.g. the effects of the emissions
of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere, we introduce a novel type of
random perturbation for the classical Lorenz flow and prove its
stochastic stability. The perturbation acts on the system in an
impulsive way, hence is not of diffusive type. Namely, given a
cross-section M for the unperturbed flow, each time the trajectory of
the system crosses M the phase velocity field is changed with a new one
sampled at random from a suitable neighborhood of the unperturbed one.
The resulting random evolution is therefore described by a piecewise
deterministic Markov process. The proof of the stochastic stability for
the unperturbed flow is then carried on working either in the framework
of the Random Dynamical Systems or in that of semi-Markov processes.
Joint work with Sandro Vaienti.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Andrea Venturelli (Université d’Avignon, France)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/andrea-venturelli-universite-davignon-france/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 09:00:26 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/andrea-venturelli-universite-davignon-france/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Andrea Venturelli&lt;/strong>  (Université d’Avignon, France)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Hyperbolic motion in the Newtonian N-body problem with
arbitrary limit shape&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> We prove for the N-body problem the existence of hyperbolic
motions for any prescribed limit shape and any given initial
configuration of the bodies. The energy level h&amp;gt;0 of the motion can
also be chosen arbitrarily. Our approach is based on the construction of
a global viscosity solutions for the Hamilton-Jacobi equation
H(x,du(x))=h. Our hyperbolic motion is in fact a calibrating curve of
the viscosity solution. The presented results can also be viewed as a
new application of Marchal&amp;rsquo;s theorem, whose main use in recent
literature has been to prove the existence of periodic orbits. Joint
work with Ezequiel Maderna.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Anna Miriam Benini (Università di Parma, Italy)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/miriam-benini-universita-di-parma-italy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 14:07:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/miriam-benini-universita-di-parma-italy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Anna Miriam Benini&lt;/strong>  (Università di Parma, Italy)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Infinite entropy for transcendental entire functions&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> Defining entropy on noncompact metric spaces is a tricky
business, since there are several natural and nonequivalent
generalizations of the usual notions of entropy for continuous maps on
compact spaces. By defining entropy for transcendental maps on the
complex plane as the sup over the entropy restricted to compact forward
invariant subsets, we prove that with this definition the entropy of
such functions is infinite. The proof relies on covering results which
are distinctive to holomorphic maps.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Isaia Nisoli (Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro, Brazil)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/isaia-nisoli-universidade-federal-de-rio-de-janeiro-brazil/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Nov 2020 15:00:18 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/isaia-nisoli-universidade-federal-de-rio-de-janeiro-brazil/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Isaia Nisoli&lt;/strong>  (Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro,
Brazil)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>A simple system presenting Noise Induced Order&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> In this talk I will present a family of one dimensional
systems with random additive noise such that, as the noise size
increases, the Lyapunov exponent of the stationary measure transitions
from positive to negative. This phenomena is known in literature as
Noise Induced Order, and was first observed in a model of the
Belosouv-Zhabotinsky reaction and its existence was proven only recently
by Galatolo-Monge-Nisoli. In the talk I will show how this phenomena is
strictly connected with non-uniform hyperbolicity and the coexistence of
regions of expansion and contraction in phase space; the result is
attained through a result on the continuity of the Lyapunov exponent of
the stationary measure with respect to the size of the noise.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Carlangelo Liverani (Università di Roma Tor Vergata, Italy)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/carlangelo-liverani-universita-di-roma-tor-vergata-italy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 13:58:20 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/carlangelo-liverani-universita-di-roma-tor-vergata-italy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Carlangelo Liverani&lt;/strong>  (Università di Roma Tor Vergata,
Italy)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Locating Ruelle-Pollicott resonances&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> We study the spectrum of transfer operators associated to
various dynamical systems. Our aim is to obtain precise information on
discrete spectrum. To this end we propose a unitary approach. We
consider various settings where new information can be obtained
following different branches along the proposed path. These settings
include affine expanding Markov maps, uniformly expanding Markov maps,
non-uniformly expanding maps, hyperbolic diffeomorphisms. We believe
this to be the germ of a general theory. Joint work with O. Butterley
and N. Kiamari.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Stefano Marò (Università di Pisa, Italy)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/stefano-maro-university-of-pisa-italy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 21:29:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/stefano-maro-university-of-pisa-italy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Stefano Marò&lt;/strong>  (Università di Pisa, Italy)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Chaotic motion in the breathing circle billiard&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> We consider the free motion of a point particle inside a
circular billiard with periodically moving boundary, with the assumption
that the collisions of the particle with the boundary are elastic so
that the energy of the particle is not preserved. It is known that if
the motion of the boundary is regular enough then the energy is bounded
due to the existence of invariant curves. We show that it is
nevertheless possible that the motion of the particle is chaotic, also
under regularity assumptions for the moving boundary. More precisely, we
show that there exists a class of functions describing the motion of the
boundary for which the billiard map admits invariant probability
measures with positive metric entropy. The proof relies on variational
techniques based on Aubry-Mather theory. Joint work with Claudio
Bonanno.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions, with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Françoise Pène (Université de Bretagne Occidentale, France)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/francoise-pene-universite-de-bretagne-occidentale-france/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 11:00:20 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/francoise-pene-universite-de-bretagne-occidentale-france/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Françoise Pène&lt;/strong> (Université de Bretagne Occidentale, France)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Invariance by induction of the asymptotic variance&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> It is well known that the integral of an observable is
preserved by induction. We are interested here in extensions of this
result to moments of order 2 and 3. We have two natural candidates for
the second and third order moments: the classical asymptotic variance
(given by the Green-Kubo formula) and an analogous quantity of the third
order. This question arises from the proof of CLT. In some cases, the
asymptotic variance in the CLT can be expressed on the one hand in terms
of the classical Green-Kubo formula and on the other hand in terms of
the Green-Kubo formula for the induced system. Under general assumptions
(involving transfer operators), we prove that the asymptotic variance is
preserved by induction and that the natural third order quantity is
preserved up to an error term. This is joint work with Damien Thomine.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Andreas Knauf (Friedrich-Alexander-Universität Erlangen-Nürnberg, Germany)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/andreas-knauf-friedrich-alexander-universitat-erlangen-nurnberg-germany/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2020 07:07:48 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/andreas-knauf-friedrich-alexander-universitat-erlangen-nurnberg-germany/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Andreas Knauf&lt;/strong> (Friedrich-Alexander-Universität Erlangen-Nürnberg, Germany)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Asymptotic velocity for scattering particles&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> Partly with Jacques Fejoz, Richard Montgomery, Stefan Fleischer and Manuel Quaschner.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The past and future of scattering particle systems is partly determined
by their asymptotic velocity, that is, the Cesàro limit of the velocity.
That this exists for bounded interactions and all initial conditions, is
part of a statement sometimes called &amp;lsquo;asymptotic completeness&amp;rsquo;. The same
statement does not apply to individual initial conditions in celestial
mechanics. However, at least for up to four particles, nonexistence of
asymptotic velocity is a measure zero phenomenon. We explain some new
ideas connected with the proof (Poincaré section techniques for
wandering sets, non-deterministic particle systems, and walks on a poset
of set partitions).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sunrose Shrestha (Tufts University, USA)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/sunrose-shrestha-tufts-university-usa/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 13:29:58 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/sunrose-shrestha-tufts-university-usa/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Sunrose Shrestha&lt;/strong>  (Tufts University, USA)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>The topology and geometry of random square-tiled surfaces&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> A square-tiled surface (STS) is a branched cover of the
standard square torus with branching over exactly one point. They are
concrete examples of translation surfaces which are an important class
of singular flat metrics on 2-manifolds with applications in Teichmüller
theory and polygonal billiards. In this talk we will consider a
randomizing model for STSs based on permutation pairs and use it to
compute the genus distribution. We also study holonomy vectors
(Euclidean displacement vectors between cone points) on a random STS.
Holonomy vectors of translation surfaces provide coordinates on the
space of translation surfaces and their enumeration up to a fixed length
has been studied by various authors such as Eskin and Masur. In this
talk, we obtain finer information about the set of holonomy vectors,
Hol(S), of a random STS. In particular, we will see how often Hol(S)
contains the set of primitive integer vectors and find how often these
sets are exactly equal.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Marta Maggioni (Universiteit Leiden, Netherlands)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/marta-maggioni-universiteit-leiden-netherlands/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 19:31:13 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/marta-maggioni-universiteit-leiden-netherlands/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Marta Maggioni&lt;/strong> (Universiteit Leiden, Netherlands)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Matching for random systems with an application to minimal weight expansions&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> We consider families of skew-product maps, representing
systems evolving in discrete time in which, at each time step, one of a
number of transformations is chosen according to an i.i.d process and
applied. We extend the notion of matching for such dynamical systems and
we show that, for a certain family of piecewise affine random maps of
the interval, the property of random matching implies that any invariant
density is piecewise constant. We give an application by introducing a
one-parameter family of random maps generating signed binary expansions
of numbers. This family has random matching for Lebesgue almost every
parameter, producing matching intervals that are related to the ones
obtained for the Nakada continued fraction transformations. We use this
property to study the expansions with minimal weight. Joint with K.
Dajani and C. Kalle.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sandro Vaienti (Centre de Physique Théorique, Marseille, France)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/sandro-vaienti-centre-de-physique-theorique-marseille-france/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 12:24:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/sandro-vaienti-centre-de-physique-theorique-marseille-france/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> **Sandro Vaienti ** (Centre de Physique Théorique, Marseille,
France)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Thermodynamic formalism for random weighted covering
systems&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> We develop a quenched thermodynamic formalism for random
dynamical systems generated by countably branched, piecewise-monotone
mappings of the interval that satisfy a random covering condition.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Joint with J. Atnip, G. Froyland and C. Gonzalez-Tokman&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Francesco Cellarosi (Queen's University, Canada)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/28-5-francesco-cellarosi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 12:22:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/28-5-francesco-cellarosi/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Francesco Cellarosi&lt;/strong>  (Queen&amp;rsquo;s University, Canada)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Rational Horocycle lifts and the tails of Quadratic Weyl
sums&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> Equidistribution of horocycles on hyperbolic surfaces has
been used to dynamically answer several probabilistic questions about
number-theoretical objects. In this talk we focus on horocycle lifts,
i.e. curves on higher-dimensional manifolds whose projection to the
hyperbolic surface is a classical horocycle, and their behaviour under
the action of the geodesic flow. It is known that when such horocycle
lifts are `generic’, then their push forward via the geodesic flow
becomes equidistributed in the ambient manifold. We consider certain
‘non-generic’ (i.e. rational) horocycle lifts, in which case the
equidistribution takes place on a sub-manifold. We then use this fact to
study the tail distribution of quadratic Weyl sums when one of their
arguments is random and the other is rational. In this case we obtain
random variables with heavy tails, all of which only possess moments of
order less than 4. Depending on the rational argument, we establish the
exact tail decay, which can be described with the help of the Dedekind
\psi-function.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Joint work with Tariq Osman.&lt;/p>
&lt;p> &lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions,  with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Martin Leguil (Université Paris-Sud 11, France)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/martin-leguil-universite-paris-sud-11-france/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 12:20:21 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/martin-leguil-universite-paris-sud-11-france/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker:&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Martin Leguil&lt;/strong> (Université Paris-Sud 11, France)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Some rigidity results for billiards and hyperbolic flows&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> In a project with P. Bálint, J. De Simoi and V. Kaloshin, we
have been studying the inverse problem for a class of open dispersing
billiards obtained by removing from the plane a finite number of smooth
strictly convex scatterers satisfying a non-eclipse condition. The
dynamics of such billiards is hyperbolic (Axiom A), and there is a
natural labeling of periodic orbits. We show that it is generically
possible, in the analytic category and for billiard tables with two
(partial) axial symmetries, to determine completely the geometry of
those billiards from the purely dynamical data encoded in their Marked
Length Spectrum (lengths of periodic orbits + marking). An important
step is the obtention of asymptotic estimates for the Lyapunov exponents
of certain periodic points accumulating a reference periodic point,
which turn out to be useful in the study of other rigidity problems. In
particular, I will explain the results obtained in a joint work with J.
De Simoi, K. Vinhage and Y. Yang on the question of entropy rigidity for
3-dimensional Anosov flows and dispersing billiards.&lt;/p>
&lt;p> &lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions,  with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Giulio Tiozzo (University of Toronto, Canada)</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/giulio-tiozzo-university-of-toronto-canada/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 12:18:03 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/dai-seminars/giulio-tiozzo-university-of-toronto-canada/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Speaker&lt;/em>: &lt;strong>Giulio Tiozzo&lt;/strong>  (University of Toronto, Canada)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Title:&lt;/em> &lt;em>&lt;strong>Central limit theorems for counting measures in coarse
negative curvature&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Abstract:&lt;/em> We establish general central limit theorems for an action of
a group on a hyperbolic space with respect to counting for the word
length in the group.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 2013, Chas, Li, and Maskit produced numerical experiments on random
closed geodesics on a hyperbolic pair of pants. Namely, they drew
uniformly at random conjugacy classes of a given word length, and
considered the hyperbolic length of the corresponding closed geodesic on
the pair of pants. Their experiments lead to the conjecture that the
length of these closed geodesics satisfies a central limit theorem, and
we proved this conjecture in 2018.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In our new work, we remove the assumptions of properness and smoothness
of the space, or cocompactness of the action, thus proving a general
central limit theorem for group actions on hyperbolic spaces.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We will see how our techniques replace the classical thermodynamic
formalism and allow us to provide new applications, including to lengths
of geodesics in geometrically finite manifolds and to intersection
numbers with submanifolds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Joint work with I. Gekhtman and S. Taylor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p> &lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>NOTE:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>The seminar will be streamed live on our &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCyNNg155G3iLS7l-qZjboyg">YouTube
channel&lt;/a> then
saved there. If you ask questions,  with your video feed on or off, you
agree to the use of your image/spoken words for said purpose.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>