<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Site on DinAmicI</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/tags/site/</link><description>Recent content in Site on DinAmicI</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 21:08:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.dinamici.org/tags/site/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to add a new publication</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/07/how-to-add-a-new-publication/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 21:08:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/07/how-to-add-a-new-publication/</guid><description>&lt;p>Keeping an up-to-date list of publications on our site is important in
terms of our visibility as DinAmicI. Adding a new publication (by you or
another member of our community) is rather straightforward, but still
here are some instructions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On your back-end page (that you get to by clicking on &amp;ldquo;Site Admin&amp;rdquo; on
any of the site&amp;rsquo;s pages), look for &amp;ldquo;Publications&amp;rdquo; in the list on the
left. In the pop-up menu, click on &amp;ldquo;Add New&amp;rdquo;. A web form will appear.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The title of your publication goes in the first field of the form, under
the header &amp;ldquo;Add a new publication&amp;rdquo;. After you&amp;rsquo;ve inserted that, select
the type of publication, typically a Journal Article. If you don&amp;rsquo;t know
better, leave the adjacent field, BibTeX Key, blank for the moment. Then
proceed to insert the authors, all separated by the word &amp;ldquo;and&amp;rdquo;, and the
Date of Publishing, in the YYYY-MM-DD format (many journals will tell
you the exact date of publication; if you can&amp;rsquo;t find it approximate it
with a date in the YYYY-MM-DD format).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After this, you can go back to the &amp;ldquo;BibTeX Key&amp;rdquo; field, and click on the
two-arrow icon next to it. This way, the form will produce a key (i.e.,
a nickname) for your publication, which is mandated by the system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Add as much information as you can in the &amp;ldquo;Detailed Information&amp;rdquo;
section. In the &amp;ldquo;Journal&amp;rdquo; field, we recommend that you put the full name
of the journal, to avoid the chance that two authors use different
abbreviations for the same journal. We like for every publication record
to have at least a link in it. One link will be produced by the DOI,
which should definitely be provided, if the publication has one (most
do, upon online publication). Other links can be provided in the
&amp;ldquo;URL/Files&amp;rdquo; field. We recommend that you put there at least one link to
a freely downloadable version of your publication (e.g., the arXiv
link). No need to upload files.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, if this is your own publication, check the &amp;ldquo;add to your own
list&amp;rdquo; box, on the right, in the &amp;ldquo;Bookmarks&amp;rdquo; section. Also, right below
that, add any tags (old and new) to make your record more easily
searchable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Of course, everything can be edited after the posting of your record.&lt;/p>
&lt;p> &lt;/p>
&lt;p> &lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How to post</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/07/how-to-post/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 08:15:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/07/how-to-post/</guid><description>&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;d like to post something on the website click on the &amp;ldquo;site admin&amp;rdquo;
link on the main page. You&amp;rsquo;ll find it under &amp;ldquo;Meta links&amp;rdquo; on the left
hand side.  This will take you to your dashboard where you&amp;rsquo;ll find a
&amp;ldquo;Posts&amp;rdquo; link on the top left. Click on the sub-link &amp;ldquo;Add New&amp;rdquo; and you&amp;rsquo;ll
be brought to a page where you can create your post.  Note that you can
add links to webpages, such as
&lt;a href="https://www.dinamici.org/">www.DinAmicI.org&lt;/a> and media files such as
pictures:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.dinamici.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/05/DAI.png">&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>by using the menu at the top.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>IMPORTANT!!! Once you&amp;rsquo;ve finished writing your post don&amp;rsquo;t forget to
choose at least one category from the categories menu on the right. Your
post will only appear on the website if it is categorised. Barring
exceptions, the category &amp;ldquo;News&amp;rdquo; should be checked for all posts,
together with possibly another category chosen among &amp;ldquo;Events&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Open
positions&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Forum&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For better indexing you can also add tags to your post.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can preview your post using the preview option found at the
top-right of the page. Once finished click on the &amp;ldquo;Publish&amp;rdquo; button and
your post will be available to see on the website. Note that you can go
back and edit your post after it has been published.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you have any questions please contact us or leave a comment.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Latex support on this website</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/02/latex-support-on-dai-website/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2015 16:41:05 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/02/latex-support-on-dai-website/</guid><description>&lt;p>This website uses &lt;a href="https://www.mathjax.org" title="MathJax">MathJax&lt;/a>, a
JavaScript library able to compile and render latex live in your
browser. The syntax is fully explained here:
&lt;a href="https://wordpress.org/plugins/mathjax-latex/">https://wordpress.org/plugins/mathjax-latex/&lt;/a>. Briefly:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li> &lt;code>display style&lt;/code> formulas can be obtained as in the standard latex
syntax by typing them between double dollars or escaped square
brackets (&lt;code>$$ ... $$&lt;/code> or &lt;code>\[ ... \]&lt;/code> );&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;code>inline style&lt;/code> formulas use the slightly non-standard syntax
&lt;code>$latex ... $&lt;/code> or &lt;code>\( ... \)&lt;/code>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p> &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Examples:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;code>$latex e^{i\pi} + 1 = 0$&lt;/code> is rendered as $latex e^{i\pi} + 1 = 0$;&lt;/li>
&lt;li> &lt;code>\(\int_0^1 x dx = \frac12\)&lt;/code> is rendered as \(\int_0^1 x dx =
\frac12 \);&lt;/li>
&lt;li>finally &lt;code> $$\|z\| = 0$$&lt;/code> is rendered as  $$\|z\| = 0.$$&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p> &lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can freely use mathematical formulas in comments and posts.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>New website</title><link>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/02/new-website/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2015 16:02:56 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.dinamici.org/2015/02/new-website/</guid><description>&lt;p>Thanks to the tireless work of our great Marcello, we now have a
wonderful shiny new site!!&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>